hey guys here's another geometry
challenge we have a square that's a two
by two square I have four circles stuck
inside of that square and there's
another Square turn 45 degrees and fit
inside those circles so that it touches
at those four points and we want to know
what is the area of this Square I think
there's two ways to solve this I kind of
want to show you both ways we'll call
one side of the square a length of s s
for side or Square then we'll draw a
little square here and we'll notice that
this square right here cuts into exactly
one-fourth of that square which means I
could probably flip it and get the same
piece right up there just like that so
this piece should equal this piece right
here if you think about how those four
squares would be cut off both of these
are exactly half of the length of s so
the two of them together should just be
S let's look at this diagonal of the
square I drew in the corner it's going
to be comprised of s plus it's a
diameter of one of these circles how
long is this diameter of this circle
well if we cut this side in half each of
these halves is equal to one and that
half is the same height as one of the
diameters so we can call this diameter
one so the diagonal of the square square
is equal to S plus one but we can pull
out of this a triangle and this green
triangle here is the same thing as this
green triangle here both of these sides
are equal to one anytime you have a
right triangle where the two legs are
equal to one the hypotenuse is always
equal to square root of two and if you
want to verify it here it is using
Pythagorean theorem so now we can plug
in square root of 2 for the diagonal and
then we can smush this together and
clean all this stuff up scoot this over
and now we can solve for S let's
subtract one from both sides and we get
S equals square root of 2 minus one s is
the side of the square to get the area
of the square that we would Square s so
we're just going to square both sides of
this equation on the left hand side
that's the same thing is multiplying
this binomial by itself and we have to
distribute so we're going to do square
root of 2 Times Square Root 2 gives us
2. root 2 times negative 1 gives us
negative root 2 and negative 1 times
root 2 gives us negative root two and
then negative 1 times negative 1 is
positive one and this is all still equal
to S squared 2 plus 1 is equal to 3 and
negative root 2 minus root 2 is minus
two root 2. so this right here is the
area of the Red Square it's 3 minus two
root 2. we can put a box around that and
let's put a box around S as well that's
seem pretty important get rid of all
this other stuff bring this down and
let's look at the other more formal way
to solve it you can find the centers of
these three circles connect the centers
we can see this piece right here is the
same thing as the side length of s
because it's the same thing as one of
the side lengths of that square then we
look up here both of these are the
radius of this top Circle so we'll call
both of those R and same thing here
these are both the radius of this circle
so we'll call those R and same thing
here both these are the Rays of that
Circle so we'll call those R now if we
extend this radius up here we'll notice
that R plus r is the same thing as one
so we just say two R equals one now
let's use Pythagorean theorem for this
right triangle if a squared plus b
squared equals c squared where a is this
bottom side here which is R plus r well
we know that R plus r is equal to one B
is this R plus r but we know that's
equal to one well C is this R plus S
Plus R and then R plus r is 2R and we
know that 2R is equal to one so we can
make that one one squared plus 1 squared
is just two then from here we square
root both sides the root and the square
cancel each other out to give us 1 plus
s when we subtract one from both sides
this side becomes root two minus one and
this side just becomes s so now we solve
for S and check this out it's the same s
that we got before so since we got the
same as both methods we know they're
both going to give us the same area so
the answer the question is the area is
equal to three minus two root 2 or in
other words
0.17157 I'm going to put units squared
so the exact value of the area of the
red square is three minus two root 2
units squared and the approximate area
of this red square is 0.17157 units
squared how exciting